<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="landing">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Edition Landing Page</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="hero" xml:lang="en" rend="two-column">
            <head><graphic url="resources/images/tei-publisher-logo-contrast-color.svg"/></head>
            <p>Sustainable publishing toolbox – rooted in standards, built by the community, meant to last</p>
            <list type="links">
               <item><ref target="#highlights">explore</ref></item>
               <item><ref target="doc/quickstart.xml">quickstart</ref></item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="about" xml:lang="en" n="About" rend="two-column">
            <head>Working environment for creating and publishing of digital scholarly
               editions</head>
            <p>TEI Publisher is designed as a working environment for creating and publishing of
               digital scholarly editions. Editions created with this framework are aiming to meet
               the varied needs of several humanities disciplines (textual scholarship, literary
               studies, linguistics, history and more). TEI Publisher builds on what is common, at
               the same time providing the choice and customisation possibilities to the editors and
               developers.</p>
            <p>The platform follows the international standard for the encoding of textual data,
               TEI, and bases its visualisations on TEI Publisher. As a result, it enables
               publication of different types of material: from the basic presentation of texts and
               documents in digital form to the most complex scholarly editions. There is room for
               various forms of textual delivery (transcriptions, translations, facsimiles) and
               annotations.</p>
            <p>Tools and working environment are not enough. To best serve the needs of editors, a
               consistent and efficient process for creating and publishing digital scholarly
               editions is needed. This project is offering such a process. It includes sets of good
               practices and workflows and takes into account both how scholarly editors work and
               how IT specialists, responsible for the technical side of editions, complete their
               tasks.</p>
         </div>
         
         <div type="highlights" xml:lang="en">
            <head>Explore</head>
            <list>
               <item n="Documentation + Demo">
                  <desc><ref target="#">Documentation and Demo</ref></desc>
                  <note>Start here to explore the features of TEI Publisher and read the extensive documentation.</note>
                  <ptr type="image" target="resources/images/books.jpg"/>
                  <list type="links">
                     <item><ref target="#">Open</ref></item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item n="Demo" corresp="https://e-editiones.org/apps/tp-serafin">
                  <desc><ref target="/exist/apps/tp-serafin">Correspondence Edition</ref></desc>
                  <note>Showcases a typical correspondence edition using the letters to Mikołaj
                     Serafin as an example. Highlights: parallel view with transcription and
                     translation, entity register of people and places, correspondence navigation
                     and a timeline.</note>
                  <ptr type="image" target="resources/images/header-bg.jpg"/>
                  <list type="links">
                     <item><ref target="/exist/apps/tp-serafin">Open</ref></item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item n="Demo" corresp="https://e-editiones.org/apps/tp-workbench">
                  <desc><ref target="/exist/apps/tp-workbench">Workbench</ref></desc>
                  <note>TEI Publisher also provides tools to simplify the edition workflow: the
                     web-based annotation editor helps to extend a base transcription with semantic
                     and other information, while JinnTap is an online editor for working directly
                     on a TEI text.</note>
                  <ptr type="image" target="resources/images/typewriter2.jpg"/>
                  <list type="links">
                     <item><ref target="/exist/apps/tp-workbench">Open</ref></item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item n="Manage">
                  <desc><ref target="/exist/apps/jinks" rend="new">Jinks</ref></desc>
                  <note>Jinks is TEI Publisher's central application manager. Use it to maintain or kickstart new applications.</note>
                  <ptr type="image" target="resources/images/library.jpg"/>
                  <list type="links">
                     <item><ref target="/exist/apps/jinks" rend="new">Open</ref></item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="section" xml:lang="en" n="About" rend="two-column">
            <head>About Us</head>
            <p>TEI Publisher is a community effort based on ideas and contributions by TEI
               enthusiasts all over the world, <ref target="https://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl-3.0.en.html">licensed under the
                  GPLv3</ref>. Initially inspired by the vision behind the TEI Processing Model -
               work of the late Sebastian Rahtz and other members of the TEI Simple project of 2015
               - it continues to evolve into what you can see today. This is only possible thanks to
               contributions of developers, users and institutions having concrete publication
               projects and willing to employ <hi rend="bold">Open Source first</hi> approach so the
               whole community can reuse and benefit from their work.</p>
            <div>
               <head>Brought to you by</head>
               <figure>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/e-editiones-logo-color-inverted.svg" width="220px"/>
               </figure>
               <p>TEI Publisher is not a <hi rend="bold">commercial project</hi>. We strongly
                  believe in Open Source, <hi rend="bold">standards and reusability</hi>. The TEI
                  Processing Model and TEI Publisher are a major step towards true interoperability,
                  reusablity and sustainability. To further promote these goals and build a strong
                  community, a number of smaller and larger edition projects, cultural heritage
                  institutions and single researchers came together in May 2020 to found
                  e-editiones.org, which now hosts the TEI Publisher source code and coordinates its
                  development.</p>

               <p>During the past few years a growing number of projects from small to large have
                  decided to publish their materials with the TEI Publisher. It gives us all not
                  only the opportunity but also the responsibility to make the project thrive for
                  years to come and to make it truly sustainable option for XML publishing!</p>

               <p>While we are very happy with the achievements so far, we still have a much broader
                  vision to fulfill. To make this happen we invite the community to contribute to
                  the project - by means of code, ideas, documentation, tutorials and funding.</p>

               <p>You don't have to be a developer to contribute, you can do so in a number of
                  ways!</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Check out the source code, modify it, document it, enhance it.</item>
                  <item>Create new or enhance existing example documents and ODDs so we present
                     showcases for various TEI applications.</item>
                  <item>Report your issues, feature requests or ideas for discussion on the issue
                     tracker.</item>
                  <item>Discuss with us on the #community room on the e-editiones slack or write to
                     the mailing list.</item>
                  <item>Port back your custimizations to the TEI Publisher code base so others can
                     use it too (or ask us to do it for you)!</item>
                  <item>Help and mentor others - publish teaching materials, answer questions on our
                     Slack channel, mailing list and other forums.</item>
                  <item>Sponsor a concrete feature or fund a development grant.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Support</head>
               <p>While we have strong evidence to prove that publishing with the TEI Publisher is a
                  really fast way to get a state of the art edition on-line it may still not be
                  everyone's cup of tea. We're there to help and we promise it will help everyone
                  else too!</p>

               <p>TEI Publisher's development so far was mainly funded by projects having concrete
                  publication needs. If you have a digital edition to publish and would like to give
                  TEI Publisher a try, contact us at Jinntec and we commit to port any feature with
                  more general interest back to the TEI Publisher.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         
         <div type="partners" xml:lang="en" n="Partners">
            <head>Project Team &amp; Partners</head>
            <p>The Jinks edition project is brought to life by</p>
            <list rend="partner-logos">
               <item>
                  <ref type="uri" target="https://jinntec.de">
                     <graphic url="resources/images/jinntec.svg"/>
                  </ref>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ref type="uri" target="https://e-editiones.org">
                     <graphic url="resources/images/e-editiones-logo-color.svg"/>
                  </ref>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ref type="uri" target="https://tei-c.org">
                     <graphic url="resources/images/tei-with-text.svg"/>
                  </ref>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>