<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="landing">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Edition Landing Page</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="hero" xml:lang="en" rend="two-column">
            <head>Jinks<hi rend="strong">edition</hi></head>
            <p>This site presents the results of the digital humanities projects created with TEI
               Publisher and Jinks. It is a part of the environment for the development of digital
               scholarly editions and a space for their presentation.</p>
            <list type="links">
               <item><ref target="#">explore</ref></item>
            </list>
         </div>
        <div type="hero" xml:lang="de" rend="two-column">
            <head>Jinks<hi rend="strong">edition</hi></head>
            <p>Diese Seite präsentiert die Ergebnisse von Projekten aus den Digital Humanities, die
               mit TEI Publisher und Jinks erstellt wurden. Sie ist Teil der Umgebung für die
               Entwicklung digitaler wissenschaftlicher Editionen und bietet einen Raum für deren
               Präsentation.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="about" xml:lang="en" n="About" rend="two-column">
            <head>Working environment for creating and publishing of digital scholarly
               editions</head>
            <p>Jinks application manager is designed as a working environment for creating and
               publishing of digital scholarly editions. Editions created with this framework are
               aiming to meet the varied needs of several humanities disciplines (textual
               scholarship, literary studies, linguistics, history and more). Jinks builds on what
               is common, at the same time providing the choice and customisation possibilities to
               the editors and developers.</p>
            <p>The platform follows the international standard for the encoding of textual data,
               TEI, and bases its visualisations on TEI Publisher. As a result, it enables
               publication of different types of material: from the basic presentation of texts and
               documents in digital form to the most complex scholarly editions. There is room for
               various forms of textual delivery (transcriptions, translations, facsimiles) and
               annotations.</p>
            <p>Tools and working environment are not enough. To best serve the needs of editors, a
               consistent and efficient process for creating and publishing digital scholarly
               editions is needed. This project is offering such a process. It includes sets of good
               practices and workflows and takes into account both how scholarly editors work and
               how IT specialists, responsible for the technical side of editions, complete their
               tasks.</p>
         </div>
        <div type="about" xml:lang="de" n="About" rend="two-column">
            <head>Arbeitsumgebung für die Erstellung und Veröffentlichung digitaler
               wissenschaftlicher Editionen</head>
            <p>Der Jinks Application Manager wurde als Arbeitsumgebung für die Erstellung und
               Veröffentlichung digitaler wissenschaftlicher Editionen konzipiert. Editionen, die
               mit diesem Framework erstellt wurden, sollen den vielfältigen Anforderungen
               verschiedener geisteswissenschaftlicher Disziplinen (Editionswissenschaft,
               Literaturwissenschaft, Linguistik, Geschichte und mehr) gerecht werden. Jinks baut
               auf einer gemeinsamen Basis auf und bietet gleichzeitig Auswahl- und Anpassungsmöglichkeiten
               für die Editorinnen und Editoren sowie Entwicklerinnen und Entwickler.</p>
            <p>Die Plattform folgt dem internationalen Standard zur Kodierung von Textdaten, TEI,
               und nutzt TEI Publisher für die Darstellung. Dadurch ermöglicht sie die
               Publikation unterschiedlichster Materialien: von der grundlegenden Präsentation von
               Texten und Dokumenten in digitaler Form bis hin zu komplexen
               wissenschaftlichen Editionen. Verschiedene Formen der Textausgabe
               (Transkriptionen, Übersetzungen, Faksimiles) und Annotationen werden unterstützt.</p>
            <p>Werkzeuge und Arbeitsumgebung allein reichen jedoch alleine nicht aus. Um den Bedürfnissen der
               Editorinnen und Editoren bestmöglich zu entsprechen, ist ein konsistenter und
               effizienter Prozess zur Erstellung und Veröffentlichung digitaler wissenschaftlicher
               Editionen erforderlich. Dieses Projekt bietet einen solchen Prozess an. Er beinhaltet
               gute Praxisbeispiele und Workflows und berücksichtigt sowohl die Arbeit wissenschaftlicher
               Editorinnen und Editoren, als auch die für die
               technische Seite der Edition verantwortlichen IT-Spezialist:innen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="highlights" xml:lang="en">
            <head>Highlights</head>
            <list>
               <item n="Corpus">
                  <desc>Collection of sources encoded with the TEI standard</desc>
                  <note>Fascinating collection of sources encoded in the TEI standard, comprising records of rulers and individuals belonging to the social elite of European states provide insight into the mechanisms of power, the relationship between the center and the peripheries of a state, and the way of life of different social groups. They reveal the mobility of their representatives, networks of contacts, and their engagement in social, political, and economic life.</note>
                  <ptr type="image" target="resources/images/books.jpg"/>
                  <list type="links">
                     <item><ref target="#">Explore</ref></item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item n="Indexes">
                  <desc>Registers of individuals and places</desc>
                  <note>Registers of individuals and places mentioned in the corpus offer a point of entry into the intricate social and geographical network of that era.</note>
                  <ptr type="image" target="resources/images/header-bg.jpg"/>
                  <list type="links">
                     <item><ref target="places">Explore</ref></item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item n="User Guide">
                  <desc>User guide</desc>
                  <note>Facets are the fastest way to conduct your searches, simply ticking a box for e.g. the Place, Country or Period that interest you. Current search results will be constrained to show only entries that match exactly all your specified criteria.</note>
                  <ptr type="image" target="resources/images/typewriter2.jpg"/>
                  <list type="links">
                     <item><ref target="places">Explore</ref></item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
        <div type="section" xml:lang="en" n="More" rend="two-column">
            <head>Other resources</head>
            <p>Use this section to provide short descriptions and links to other resources in the
               collection.</p>
            <p>The Jinks edition project is brought to life by a dedicated team of historians,
               digital archivists, and designers passionate about Renaissance history</p>
            <div>
               <head>Collection of sources encoded with the TEI standard</head>
               <p>Fascinating collection of sources encoded in the TEI standard, comprising records
                  of rulers and individuals belonging to the social elite of European states provide
                  insight into the mechanisms of power, the relationship between the center and the
                  peripheries of a state, and the way of life of different social groups. They
                  reveal the mobility of their representatives, networks of contacts, and their
                  engagement in social, political, and economic life.</p>
               <list type="links">
                  <item><ref target="#" rend="explore-link">Explore</ref></item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Collection of sources encoded with the TEI standard</head>
               <p>Fascinating collection of sources encoded in the TEI standard, comprising records
                  of rulers and individuals belonging to the social elite of European states, which provide
                  insight into the mechanisms of power, the relationship between the center and the
                  peripheries of a state, and the way of life of different social groups. They
                  reveal the mobility of their representatives, networks of contacts, and their
                  engagement in social, political, and economic life.</p>
               <list type="links">
                  <item><ref target="#" rend="explore-link">Explore</ref></item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
        <div type="section" xml:lang="de" n="More" rend="two-column">
            <head>Weitere Ressourcen</head>
            <p>Nutzen Sie diesen Abschnitt für kurze Beschreibungen und Links zu weiteren Ressourcen
               in der Sammlung.</p>
            <p>Das Jinks-Editionsprojekt wird von einem engagierten Team aus Historiker:innen,
               digitalen Archivar:innen und Designer:innen entwickelt, die sich für die Geschichte der
               Renaissance begeistern.</p>
            <div>
               <head>Sammlung von Quellen im TEI-Standard kodiert</head>
               <p>Faszinierende Sammlung von Quellen nach TEI-Standard, inklusive
                  Aufzeichnungen von Herrschern und Angehörigen der gesellschaftlichen Elite
                  europäischer Staaten, die Einblick geben in die Mechanismen von Macht, das
                  Verhältnis zwischen Zentrum und Peripherie eines Staates und die Lebensweise
                  verschiedener gesellschaftlicher Gruppen. Die Quellen offenbaren die Mobilität
                  ihrer Vertreter:innen, die Netzwerke von Kontakten und deren Engagement im
                  sozialen, politischen und wirtschaftlichen Leben.</p>
               <p><ref target="#" rend="explore-link">Entdecken</ref></p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Sammlung von Quellen im TEI-Standard kodiert</head>
               <p>Faszinierende Sammlung von Quellen nach TEI-Standard, inklusive
                  Aufzeichnungen von Herrschern und Angehörigen der gesellschaftlichen Elite
                  europäischer Staaten, die Einblick geben in die Mechanismen von Macht, das
                  Verhältnis zwischen Zentrum und Peripherie eines Staates und die Lebensweise
                  verschiedener gesellschaftlicher Gruppen. Die Quellen offenbaren die Mobilität
                  ihrer Vertreter:innen, die Netzwerke von Kontakten und deren Engagement im
                  sozialen, politischen und wirtschaftlichen Leben.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="team" xml:lang="en" n="Core Team">
            <head>Team</head>
            <p>The Jinks edition project is brought to life by a dedicated team of historians,
               digital archivists, and designers passionate about Renaissance history</p>
            <listPerson>
               <person n="project managment">
                  <persName>Coco</persName>
                  <occupation>System architect</occupation>
                  <ptr type="avatar" target="resources/images/team/dog.jpg"/>
                  <note>Happily fetches new features while herding the pack towards technical
                     excellence.</note>
               </person>
            </listPerson>
            <listOrg>
               <org n="e-editiones">
                  <orgName>e-editiones</orgName>
                  <roleName>Scholarly society</roleName>
                  <ptr type="logo" target="resources/images/e-editiones-logo-color.svg"/>
                  <ptr type="email" target="mailto:info@e-editiones.org"/>
                  <note><ref target="https://www.e-editiones.org/">e-editiones</ref> is an
                     international non profit society bringing together edition projects, cultural
                     heritage institutions, scholars, and developers to empower digital projects by
                     promoting open standards and community collaboration – with the ultimate goal
                     of helping to sustain editions far into the future.</note>
               </org>
               <org n="jinntec">
                  <orgName>Jinntec GmbH</orgName>
                  <roleName>Software solutions</roleName>
                  <ptr type="logo" target="resources/images/jinntec.svg"/>
                  <ptr type="email" target="mailto:info@jinntec.de"/>
                  <note>Software solutions with a touch of magic: we believe in the importance of
                     cultural heritage - our tools help to preserve and disseminate it with
                     sustainable technologies based on Open Source software and Open Standard. From
                     assisted production workflows and data curation to publishing online or in
                     print - <ref target="https://www.jinntec.de/">we have you covered</ref>.</note>
               </org>
            </listOrg>
         </div>
         <div type="team" xml:lang="de" n="Core Team">
            <head>Team</head>
            <p>Das Jinks-Editionsprojekt wird von einem engagierten Team aus Historiker:innen,
               digitalen Archivar:innen und Designer:innen verwirklicht, die für die Geschichte der
               Renaissance begeistert sind.</p>
            <listPerson>
               <person n="project managment">
                  <persName>Coco</persName>
                  <occupation>Systemarchitektin</occupation>
                  <ptr type="avatar" target="resources/images/team/dog.jpg"/>
                  <note>Fängt mit Begeisterung neue Features und führt das Rudel zu technischer
                     Exzellenz.</note>
               </person>
            </listPerson>
            <listOrg>
               <org n="e-editiones">
                  <orgName>e-editiones</orgName>
                  <roleName>Wissenschaftliche Gesellschaft</roleName>
                  <ptr type="logo" target="resources/images/e-editiones-logo-color.svg"/>
                  <ptr type="email" target="mailto:info@e-editiones.org"/>
                  <note><ref target="https://www.e-editiones.org/">e-editiones</ref> ist eine
                     internationale, gemeinnützige Gesellschaft, die Editionsprojekte, kulturelle
                     Institutionen, Wissenschaftler:innen und Entwickler:innen zusammenbringt, um
                     digitale Projekte zu unterstützen – durch die Förderung offener Standards und
                     gemeinschaftlicher Zusammenarbeit, mit dem Ziel, Editionen langfristig zu
                     erhalten.</note>
               </org>
               <org n="jinntec">
                  <orgName>Jinntec GmbH</orgName>
                  <roleName>Softwarelösungen</roleName>
                  <ptr type="logo" target="resources/images/jinntec.svg"/>
                  <ptr type="email" target="mailto:info@jinntec.de"/>
                  <note>Softwarelösungen mit einem Hauch Magie: Wir glauben an die Bedeutung des
                     kulturellen Erbes – unsere Werkzeuge helfen, es mithilfe nachhaltiger
                     Technologien auf Basis von Open Source Software und offenen Standards zu
                     bewahren und zu verbreiten. Von unterstützten Produktions-Workflows und
                     Datenkurationsdiensten bis hin zur Online- oder Print-Publikation – <ref target="https://www.jinntec.de/">wir bieten für alles eine
                     Lösung</ref>.</note>
               </org>
            </listOrg>
         </div>
         <div type="partners" xml:lang="en" n="Partners">
            <head>Project Team &amp; Partners</head>
            <p>The Jinks edition project is brought to life by a dedicated team of historians, digital archivists, and designers passionate about Renaissance history.</p>
            <list rend="partner-logos">
               <item>
                  <ref type="uri" target="https://jinntec.de">
                     <graphic url="resources/images/jinntec.svg"/>
                  </ref>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ref type="uri" target="https://e-editiones.org">
                     <graphic url="resources/images/e-editiones-logo-color.svg"/>
                  </ref>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ref type="uri" target="https://tei-c.org">
                     <graphic url="resources/images/tei-with-text.svg"/>
                  </ref>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ref type="uri" target="https://teipublisher.org">
                     <graphic url="resources/images/tei-publisher-logo-color.svg"/>
                  </ref>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>