<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?teipublisher odd="docbook.odd"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.0">
    <info>
        <title>TEI Publisher 6.0.0</title>
        <author>
            <personname>
                <surname>Turska</surname>
                <firstname>Magdalena</firstname>
            </personname>
        </author>
        <pubdate>2020-07-07</pubdate>
        <abstract>
            <para>This is a major release introducing the refactored and extended TEI Publisher
                component library as well as numerous bugfixes and new features.</para>
        </abstract>
        <keywordset vocab="#genre">
            <keyword>Article</keyword>
        </keywordset>
    </info>
    <section>
        <title>Release Highlight: pb-components as an independent library</title>
        <para>Publisher's library of web components is now based on lightweight
                <emphasis>LitElement</emphasis> framework and available on npm. While invisible to
            users, this redesign greatly improved modularity of Publisher-based applications.</para>
        <para>Thanks to npm releases, updating the user interface for all Publisher-based apps
            becomes simply a question of changing a single variable in the configuration
            file.</para>
        <para>Furthermore, Publisher's library of web components - true to the basic idea of Web
            Components Standard - can be included in any HTML webpage. This means it can be embedded
            into existing CMS or any other publishing solution, even if it's not running eXist-db.
            Similarly, if you prefer to write your own application using any of the popular
            frameworks like <emphasis>angular</emphasis>, <emphasis>vue</emphasis> or
                <emphasis>react</emphasis> you can easily import the pb-components package from npm
            and use it directly in your project.</para>
        <para>As a final consequence, this change decouples the component library from the TEI
            Publisher app. It is now possible to host multiple applications, which depend on
            different versions of the component library, without conflict, within the same eXist-db
            instance, a point of importance for institutions with numerous projects. </para>
        
        <informalfigure>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="mei-demo.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Main New Features and Bug Fixes</title>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Redesigned and simplified CSS styling customization</para>
                <para>styling properties are exposed via standard CSS files and theme variables.
                    Stylesheets can also be specified within the ODD, as previously, or through
                        <code>pb-view</code> component configuration attributes.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Extended internationalization</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>full i18n support for all the labels in HTML templates and within web
                            components</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>mechanism for project specific language files extending the default
                            Publisher collection</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>a number of new languages added and existing ones updated. Currently
                            TEI Publisher is fully translated into Bulgarian, Czech, Dutch, French,
                            Georgian, German, Greek, Italian, Norwegian, Polish, Portuguese,
                            Romanian, Russian, Slovenian, Spanish, Swedish, Turkish and
                            Ukrainian.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <!-- Finnish Chinese Hebrew Hungarian Japanese Serbian Welsh -->
                </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Subcorpora - new TEI Publisher data organization</para>
                <para>Publisher's pre-populated data collection is now split into Playground and TEI
                    Publisher demo collection areas which illustrate how this mechanism could be
                    used to host multiple subcorpora within single TEI Publisher application.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>New and improved web components</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><code>pb-select-feature</code> and <code>pb-toggle-feature</code>
                            components have been extended to allow for interactive changing of
                            display parameters (like switching between regularized or original
                            spelling) which can be then processed client or server-side.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>new components for API documentation app and web component demo
                            pages</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><code>pb-mei</code> component for rendering Music Encoding Initiative
                            documents based on <emphasis>Verovio</emphasis>. Supports optional MIDI
                            playback using <emphasis>web-midi-player</emphasis>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Experimental incremental scroll</para>
                <para>improve performance for very long documents presented in single page
                    mode</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>ODD editor user interface improvements</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Documentation:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>reorganized and extended TEI Publisher documentation</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>pb-components API documentation and demos</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

        </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Get It!</title>
        <para>TEI Publisher 6.0.0 is available as an application package on top of the <link
                xlink:href="https://exist-db.org">eXist XML Database</link>. Install it into a
            recent eXist (5.0.0 or newer) by going to the dashboard and selecting TEI Publisher from
            the package manager.</para>
        <para>For more information refer to the <link
                xlink:href="https://teipublisher.com/exist/apps/tei-publisher/doc/documentation.xml"
                >documentation</link> or visit the <link xlink:href="https://teipublisher.com"
                >homepage</link> to play around with it.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Thanks</title>
        <para>Our thanks go to <link xlink:href="https://www.nie-ine.ch/">Nationalen Infrastruktur
                für Editionen - Infrastructure nationale pour les éditions</link> for funding a
            large part of work on the LitElement refactoring.</para>
        <para>We are also grateful to the generous contributions of numerous individuals who used
            the <link xlink:href="https://crwd.in/tei-publisher">Crowdin platform</link> to
            translate and proofread Publisher's language files: Boris Lehečka, Øyvind Gjesdal,
            Sandra Romano Martin, Antonio Rojas Castro, Isabel Marti, Natalia Kotsyba, Elena
            Spadini, Pietro Liuzzo, Karolina Bielenin-Lenczowska, Jaqueline Pierazzo, Emmanuelle
            Morlock, Emmanuel Château-Dutier, Clement Plancq, Eduard Drenth, Wout Dillen, Anna-Maria
            Sichani, Maria Akritidou, Elli Mylonas, Matija Ogrin, Cristina Vertan, Dimitar Illiev,
            Arman Weidenmann, Leif-Jöran Olsson, Irina Lobzhanidze, Joseph Wicentowski, Juri Leino,
            Daniel Stoekl, Yael Netzer, Naoki Kokaze, Kiyonori Nagasaki, Toma Tasovac, Alexandra von
            Criegern, Bettina Pandula, Daria Elagina, and others whom we unfortunately only know by
            their usernames.</para>
    </section>
</article>
