<?xml-model href="https://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd"?>
<?teipublisher odd="docbook.odd"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
    <info>
        <title>TEI Publisher 7.1.0</title>
        <author>
            <personname>
                <surname>Turska</surname>
                <firstname>Magdalena</firstname>
            </personname>
        </author>
        <pubdate>2021-08-10</pubdate>
        <abstract>
            <para>Version 7.1.0 of the TEI Publisher boasting in-browser annotations support along other features and bugfixes.</para>
        </abstract>
        <keywordset vocab="#genre">
            <keyword>Article</keyword>
        </keywordset>
    </info>


    <section>
        <title>Release Highlight: Annotations</title>
        <para>Answering the secret dream of many TEI users this new TEI Publisher version 7.1.0 incorporates
            a — beautifully simple to use, yet powerful — way to enrich existing TEI documents. Users can just
            select a text passage, click on a button and within seconds — and without a pointy bracket in sight! —
            mark it as one of many supported annotation types. A place or person? Sure, and with built-in connectors
            for external authority files, too. Critical apparatus entries? We got you! Dates, corrections, regularizations and
            even quick fixes for typos in your transcription.</para>
        <para>As usual, everything is customizable and extendable, so if you want a particular kind of annotation we
            do not support out of the box, it's not difficult to add your own or tinker existing ones. Read more in the
            <link  xlink:show="new" xlink:href="https://teipublisher.com/exist/apps/tei-publisher/doc/documentation.xml?id=web-annotations">documentation</link>
        </para>
        <informalfigure>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="ann-madrid.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Release Highlight: support for mathematical formulae</title>
        <para>You can now use the TEI <code>formula</code> element with TeX notation for mathematical formulae, so something like
        </para>
            <programlisting language="xml" xml:space="preserve">
                &lt;formula notation="TeX"&gt;\frac{24}{20 - x}&lt;/formula&gt;
                          </programlisting>
        <para>can be nicely rendered in HTML thanks to the new <code>pb-formula</code> component. See the component's 
            <link  xlink:show="new" xlink:href="https://unpkg.com/@teipublisher/pb-components@1.24.17/dist/api.html#pb-formula.1">demo page</link>
            which presents some elaborate formulae. 
        </para> 
       
        <informalfigure>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="ann-euler.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>
    </section>
    
    <section>
        <title>Other Improvements</title>
        <para>The Demo collection has several new examples, most notably a Music Encoding Initiative (MEI) example 
            <emphasis>The Italienische Madrigal</emphasis> by Alfred (not Albert!) Einstein, with musical scores encoded with MEI
            music notation. It is nicely rendered with Verovio library through a dedicated <code>pb-mei</code> component and you can even listen to it. 
            Other point of interest is the Euler's Algebra with mathematic formulas rendered via <code>pb-formula</code> component.
        </para>
        <para>Publisher 7.1.0 is available in 21 languages, now proudly boasting both simplified and traditional Chinese. We'll be happy to collaborate 
            on extending the coverage for other, especially non-European languages.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Upgrading</title>
        <para>Version 7.1.0 is fully compatible with 7 except for some minor changes which are described in the 
            <link  xlink:show="new" xlink:href="https://teipublisher.com/exist/apps/tei-publisher/doc/documentation.xml?id=upgrade7">documentation</link>.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Get It!</title>
        <para>TEI Publisher 7.1.0 is available as an application package on top of the <link xlink:href="https://exist-db.org" xlink:show="new">eXist XML Database</link>. Install it into a
            recent eXist (5.0.0 or newer) by going to the dashboard and selecting TEI Publisher from
            the package manager.</para>
        <para>For more information refer to the <link xlink:href="https://teipublisher.com/exist/apps/tei-publisher/doc/documentation.xml">documentation</link> or visit the <link xlink:href="https://teipublisher.com">homepage</link> to play around with it.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Thanks</title>
        <para>It's not for the first time that our special thanks go to the 
            <link xlink:href="https://history.state.gov/" xlink:show="new">Office of the Historian of the United States Department of State </link> - 
            this time for spearheading and funding the efforts which resulted in the annotation editor.</para>
        
        <para>The Math support has been kindly funded by <link xlink:href="https://bez.unibas.ch/de/" xlink:show="new">Bernoulli-Euler Zentrum in Basel</link>.
            </para>
    </section>
</article>