<?xml-model href="https://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd"?>
<?teipublisher odd="docbook.odd"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
    <info>
        <title>TEI Publisher 7.0.0</title>
        <author>
            <personname>
                <surname>Turska</surname>
                <firstname>Magdalena</firstname>
            </personname>
        </author>
        <pubdate>2020-12-18</pubdate>
        <abstract>
            <para>Version 7 of the TEI Publisher released with Open API and Markdown support along numerous other features and bugfixes.</para>
        </abstract>
        <keywordset vocab="#genre">
            <keyword>Article</keyword>
        </keywordset>
    </info>


    <section>
        <title>Release Highlight: Open API</title>
        <para>Version 7 represents the logical next step on our mission to improve 
            interoperability, sustainability and long-term maintenance of editions created with TEI Publisher. 
            A major redesign to the server side allowed us to expose a well-defined, clear 
            <link xlink:href="../../api.html" xlink:show="new">API specification</link> 
            following the Open API standard. Integrated Swagger UI allows you to visualize and interact with 
            the API’s resources. 
            Read more in <link xlink:href="tei-publisher-70.xml">7.0.0 Release Candidate notice</link>.
        </para>
        <para>The API can be easily extended to cover project-specific functionality.</para>
        <informalfigure>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../api-spec.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Release Highlight: Markdown support</title>
        <para>In addition to various XML vocabularies, like TEI or DocBook, you can now use Markdown format. 
            Markdown documents with <parameter>.md</parameter> extension will be correctly rendered via 
            <link xlink:href="https://marked.js.org/" xlink:show="new">marked</link> library. This feature is particularly 
            useful for static content, like introductory material or project news.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Release Highlight: Flexible collection configuration</title>
        <para>Previous versions of TEI Publisher allowed the view configuration to be specified either on the app level, 
            through default odd, template and related variables in <parameter>modules/config.xqm</parameter>, or on the 
            document level via processing instructions.
            Current version extends the application configuration mechanism in the <parameter>$config:collection-config</parameter> 
            allowing for specifying view parameters per collection or document with arbitrary filtering expression 
            (e.g. only documents in a certain language or of a particular type) without the need to change documents themselves.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Other Improvements</title>
        <para>The webcomponent library saw a number of important bug fixes and improvements. Despite the API changes, the library
            is fully backwards compatible: it first checks which version of TEI Publisher is running on the server and adjusts accordingly.</para>
        <para>Among other things we improved the component handling file uploads, introduced a way to navigate back to the parent collection
            of a document being viewed, switched to xml:id based navigation where available, fixed bugs in the visual ODD editor, the search component and many others.</para>
        <para>Furthermore we have fixed some issues with DocBook configuration, introduced more sensible defaults for indexing and sorting and 
            streamlined naming conventions of commonly customized modules. Support for nested footnotes has been improved.</para>
        <para>Publisher 7 is available in 20 languages and we'll be happy to collaborate on extending the coverage for other, 
            especially non-European languages. Extended FAQ section has been moved to an 
            <link xlink:href="https://faq.teipublisher.com/" xlink:show="new">external site</link>,
             automatically generated from markdown files stored in 
             <link xlink:href="https://github.com/eeditiones/tei-publisher-faq/tree/master/content" xlink:show="new">tei-publisher-faq</link>
             repository. Quick edits are possible via GitHub, all contributions are welcome.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Upgrading</title>
        <para>While version 7 tries to ensure that future updates will become much smoother, upgrading to 7 does still
            require a few manual steps, which are described in the 
            <link xlink:href="https://teipublisher.com/exist/apps/tei-publisher/doc/documentation.xml?id=update6-7">documentation</link>.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Get It!</title>
        <para>TEI Publisher 7.0.0 is available as an application package on top of the <link xlink:href="https://exist-db.org" xlink:show="new">eXist XML Database</link>. Install it into a
            recent eXist (5.0.0 or newer) by going to the dashboard and selecting TEI Publisher from
            the package manager.</para>
        <para>For more information refer to the <link xlink:href="https://teipublisher.com/exist/apps/tei-publisher/doc/documentation.xml">documentation</link> or visit the <link xlink:href="https://teipublisher.com">homepage</link> to play around with it.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Thanks</title>
        <para>Again our special thanks go to the <link xlink:href="https://www.nie-ine.ch/" xlink:show="new">Swiss Nationale Infrastruktur für Editionen 
            - Infrastructure nationale pour les éditions</link> for funding most of the redesign!</para>
        <para>
            <link xlink:href="https://www.nie-ine.ch/" xlink:show="new">
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/1b2bb4_a4d1727a7b92487cab792795839cfd5a~mv2_d_2362_2362_s_2.jpg/v1/crop/x_0,y_629,w_2362,h_964/fill/w_152,h_60,al_c,q_80,usm_0.66_1.00_0.01/1b2bb4_a4d1727a7b92487cab792795839cfd5a~mv2_d_2362_2362_s_2.webp"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
            </link>
        </para>
        <para>The Open API implementation was inspired
            by earlier work funded by <link xlink:href="https://uni-heidelberg.de/ecpo" xlink:show="new">Early Chinese Periodicals Online</link> (ECPO).
            A lot of bug fixes were supported by the <link xlink:href="https://www.ssrq-sds-fds.ch/home/" xlink:show="new">Sammlung Schweizerischer Rechtsquellen</link>.</para>
    </section>
</article>