<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?teipublisher odd="docbook.odd"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.0">
    <info>
        <title>TEI Publisher 6.0.0</title>
        <author>
            <personname>
                <surname>Turska</surname>
                <firstname>Magdalena</firstname>
            </personname>
        </author>
        <pubdate>2020-07-07</pubdate>
        <abstract>
            <para>This is a major release introducing the refactored and extended TEI Publisher
                component library as well as numerous bugfixes and new features.</para>
        </abstract>
        <keywordset vocab="#genre">
            <keyword>Article</keyword>
        </keywordset>
    </info>
    <section>
        <title>Release Highlight: User Interface Components as an Independent Library</title>
        <para>Publisher's library of web components is now distributed via <link xlink:href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/@teipublisher/pb-components"
                >npm</link>. Thanks to the increasing support for the web component standards in modern browsers, the heavier framework used before (Polymer)
            could be dropped and has been replaced by LitElement, which is just a thin wrapper around native web components. While invisible to users, this
            redesign greatly improves modularity of Publisher-based applications.</para>
        <para>Thanks to npm releases, updating the user interface for all Publisher-based apps
            becomes simply a question of changing a single variable in the configuration
            file.</para>
        <para>Furthermore, Publisher's library of web components - true to the basic idea of Web Components Standard - can be included in any HTML webpage. This
            means it can be embedded into existing CMS or any other publishing solution, even if it's not running eXist-db (e.g. the popular <link
                xlink:href="https://teipublisher.onrender.com/post/embedding-publisher/">Hugo</link> or <link xlink:href="https://e-editiones.org/blog/"
                >WordPress</link>). A few lines of HTML is sufficient to embed a document view anywhere you like:</para>
        <programlisting role="codepen" xlink:href="wolfgangmm#GRJyvNY"/>
        <para>Similarly, if you prefer to write your own application using any of the popular frameworks like <emphasis>angular</emphasis>,
                <emphasis>vue</emphasis> or <emphasis>react</emphasis> you can easily import the pb-components package and use it directly <link
                xlink:href="https://github.com/eeditiones/pb-extension-template">in your project</link>.</para>
        <para>As a final consequence, this change decouples the component library from the TEI
            Publisher app. It is now possible to host multiple applications, which depend on
            different versions of the component library, without conflict, within the same eXist-db
            instance, a point of importance for institutions with numerous projects. </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Main New Features and Bug Fixes</title>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Redesigned and simplified CSS styling customization</para>
                <para>Styling properties are now exposed via standard CSS files and theme variables. Stylesheets can also be specified within the ODD, as
                    previously, or through <code>pb-view</code> component configuration attributes.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Extended internationalization</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>full i18n support for all the labels in HTML templates and within web
                            components</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>mechanism for project specific language files extending the default
                            Publisher collection</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>a number of new languages added and existing ones updated. Currently
                            TEI Publisher is fully translated into Bulgarian, Czech, Dutch, French,
                            Georgian, German, Greek, Italian, Norwegian, Polish, Portuguese,
                            Romanian, Russian, Slovenian, Spanish, Swedish, Turkish and
                            Ukrainian.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <!-- Finnish Chinese Hebrew Hungarian Japanese Serbian Welsh -->
                </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Subcorpora - new TEI Publisher data organization</para>
                <para>Publisher's pre-populated data collection is now split into Playground and TEI
                    Publisher demo collection areas which illustrate how this mechanism could be
                    used to host multiple subcorpora within single TEI Publisher application.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>New and improved web components</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><code>pb-select-feature</code> and <code>pb-toggle-feature</code>
                            components have been extended to allow for interactive changing of
                            display parameters (like switching between regularized or original
                            spelling) which can be then processed client or server-side</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>new <link xlink:href="https://unpkg.com/@teipublisher/pb-components@latest/dist/api.html">API documentation app</link> and web
                            component demo pages</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><code><link xlink:href="https://unpkg.com/@teipublisher/pb-components@1.0.0/dist/api.html#pb-mei.1">pb-mei</link></code> component
                            for rendering Music Encoding Initiative documents based on <emphasis>Verovio</emphasis>; supports optional MIDI playback using
                                <emphasis>web-midi-player</emphasis></para>
                        <informalfigure>
                            <mediaobject>
                                <imageobject>
                                    <imagedata fileref="mei-demo.png"/>
                                </imageobject>
                            </mediaobject>
                        </informalfigure>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Redesigned ODD editor providing an improved user experience</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Documentation:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>reorganized and extended TEI Publisher documentation</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>pb-components API documentation and demos</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

        </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Get It!</title>
        <para>TEI Publisher 6.0.0 is available as an application package on top of the <link
                xlink:href="https://exist-db.org">eXist XML Database</link>. Install it into a
            recent eXist (5.0.0 or newer) by going to the dashboard and selecting TEI Publisher from
            the package manager.</para>
        <para>For more information refer to the <link
                xlink:href="https://teipublisher.com/exist/apps/tei-publisher/doc/documentation.xml"
                >documentation</link> or visit the <link xlink:href="https://teipublisher.com"
                >homepage</link> to play around with it.</para>
        <para>A 3-part online course on TEI Publisher 6 has been led by Wolfgang Meier in June 2020.
            Course material, as well as video recordings of all the sessions, and a walk-through for
            the assignments are available for self-learning. Find all informations on the <link
                xlink:show="new" xlink:href="https://github.com/eeditiones/workshop#slides">workshop
                GitHub</link> page. </para>
        <mediaobject>
            <videoobject>
                <videodata fileref="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/QuWrfAS2SWM" depth="480px" width="100%"/>
            </videoobject>
        </mediaobject>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Thanks</title>
        <para>Our thanks go to the Swiss <link xlink:href="https://www.nie-ine.ch/">Nationale Infrastruktur für Editionen - Infrastructure nationale pour les
                éditions</link> for funding a large part of work on the web component refactoring.</para>
        <para>Work on components for toggling has been aided by a small grant from <emphasis>ACE –
                Austrian Corpora and Editions</emphasis> of the <emphasis>Österreichische Akademie
                der Wissenschaften</emphasis>.</para>
        <para>We are also grateful for the generous contributions of numerous individuals who used
            the <link xlink:href="https://crwd.in/tei-publisher">Crowdin platform</link> to
            translate and proofread Publisher's language files: Boris Lehečka, Øyvind Gjesdal,
            Sandra Romano Martin, Antonio Rojas Castro, Isabel Marti, Natalia Kotsyba, Elena
            Spadini, Pietro Liuzzo, Karolina Bielenin-Lenczowska, Jaqueline Pierazzo, Emmanuelle
            Morlock, Emmanuel Château-Dutier, Clement Plancq, Eduard Drenth, Wout Dillen, Anna-Maria
            Sichani, Maria Akritidou, Elli Mylonas, Matija Ogrin, Cristina Vertan, Dimitar Illiev,
            Arman Weidenmann, Leif-Jöran Olsson, Irina Lobzhanidze, Joseph Wicentowski, Juri Leino,
            Daniel Stoekl, Yael Netzer, Naoki Kokaze, Kiyonori Nagasaki, Toma Tasovac, Alexandra von
            Criegern, Bettina Pandula, Daria Elagina, and others whom we unfortunately only know by
            their usernames.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>e-editiones</title>
        <para>May of 2020 saw an advent of a new scholarly society: <link xlink:href="https://e-editiones.org" xlink:show="new">e-editiones</link>. Its goal is
            to promote open standards for digital editions and free software based on them with a focus on TEI Publisher development. All TEI Publisher source
            repositories have been moved to the <link xlink:href="https://github.com/eeditiones">e-editiones github</link>.</para>
        <para>We encourage you to join the society, through your institution or individually, and
            take part in our work and discussions, shaping the future of the TEI Publisher.</para>
        <para>
            <link xlink:href="https://e-editiones.org" xlink:show="new"><informalfigure>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="e-editiones-logo-color-for-light-bg-05.png"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </informalfigure>
            </link>
        </para>
    </section>
</article>
