<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?teipublisher odd="docbook.odd"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
    <info>
        <title>TEI Publisher 4.0</title>
        <author>
            <personname>
                <surname>Meier</surname>
                <firstname>Wolfgang</firstname>
            </personname>
        </author>
        <pubdate>2018-12-20</pubdate>
        <abstract>
            <para>eXist Solutions are proud to announce the final 4.0 release of TEI Publisher. This
                release is the next big step towards our vision of a tool which enables XML-savy
                scholars and editors to publish materials without becoming programmers or forcing them
                into a one-size-fits-it-all framework.</para>
        </abstract>
        <keywordset vocab="#genre">
            <keyword>Article</keyword>
        </keywordset>
    </info>
    <section>
        <title>TEI Publisher goes Web Components</title>
        <para>Past projects we realized could prove that the
            <link xlink:href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/de/html/TD.html#TDPM">TEI Processing Model</link> is indeed a truly universal and powerful tool for any kind of  XML,
            not just TEI. However, creating an online edition requires more than just text
            transformation: the text needs to be embedded into an application context, adding
            navigation, pagination, search, facsimiles and so on. Moving towards the emerging
            web component standard, TEI Publisher 4.0 implements all this functionality as small
            "lego" blocks to be freely arranged, recombined and extended.</para>
        <para>Earlier versions of TEI Publisher were limited to showing a single text view by
            default. Creating more complex layouts required at least basic XQuery, HTML and CSS
            skills. As <link xlink:href="https://teipublisher.com/exist/apps/tei-publisher/index.html">showcased</link> by the example documents, the new version allows users to realize
            custom views without actually writing code. Users can pick from a toolbox of ready-made
            components, including text views based on an ODD transformation, IIIF-powered image
            viewers, maps and many more. All those building blocks come as custom HTML elements,
            which are easy to write and configure. Each of them encapsulates a certain functionality
            and appearance. Have a look at the <link
                xlink:href="https://teipublisher.com/exist/apps/tei-publisher/doc/documentation.xml?id=webcomponents"
                >documentation</link> and the web components API to see how to use
            components.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Open Source</title>
        <para>We strongly believe in Open Source, standards and reusability. TEI Publisher is a
            major milestone towards our vision, but there's always more to be done and we would like
            to invite the community to contribute ideas, goals and implementations. Missing a
            certain functionality or component? Tell us.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Get It!</title>
        <para>TEI Publisher 4.0 is available as an application package on top of the <link xlink:href="https://exist-db.org">eXist XML Database</link>. Install it
            into a recent eXist (4.x.x series) by going to the dashboard and selecting TEI Publisher from the package
            manager.</para>
        <para>For more information refer to the <link xlink:href="https://teipublisher.com/exist/apps/tei-publisher/doc/documentation.xml">documentation</link> or visit the <link xlink:href="https://teipublisher.com">homepage</link> to play around with it.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Thanks</title>
        <para>Our special thanks go to the erabbinica.org project for funding a major part of the
            migration to web components.</para>
    </section>
</article>
