<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?teipublisher odd="docbook.odd"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
    <info>
        <title>TEI Publisher 4.1.0</title>
        <author>
            <personname>
                <surname>Meier</surname>
                <firstname>Wolfgang</firstname>
            </personname>
        </author>
        <pubdate>2019-02-21</pubdate>
        <abstract>
            <para>This is mainly a bug fix release based on user feedback, but also includes various enhancements
                and features new demos.</para>
        </abstract>
        <keywordset vocab="#genre">
            <keyword>Article</keyword>
        </keywordset>
    </info>
    <section>
        <title>Release Highlights: Dynamic Layout and Custom Translation Alignment</title>
        <para>Many users were interested in the correspondence examples, in particular the Serafin
            and Cortés letters showing transcription and translation side by side. We have
            focused on enhancing those use cases and close some gaps in functionality. One problem
            arising in many TEI projects is how to align two or more texts, e.g. a transcription and
            a translation. In the simplest case, the texts may be aligned on the level of divisions
            or page breaks. Unfortunately things are not always as simple as that. TEI allows a wide
            variety of alignment mechanisms, some more complex than others. TEI Publisher 4.1.0 thus
            implements a generic mechanism to define a <link xlink:href="../documentation.xml?id=alignment">mapping function</link> written in XQuery. This is a
            simple, yet powerful approach. The letter from <link xlink:href="../../test/cortes_to_dantiscus_Mexico.xml">Cortés to Dantiscus (Mexico)</link>
            showcases a rather complex mapping.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Van Gogh: Dynamic, Multi Column Example</title>
        <informalfigure>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="VanGogh.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>
        <para>The <link xlink:href="http://vangoghletters.org/vg/">Van Gogh edition</link> is often
            considered a
            model example for correspondence and several users expressed their wish to create
            something similar with TEI Publisher. With recent release of XML sources for all the letters
            we've decided to use one letter from <link xlink:href="../../test/let695.xml">Van Gogh to Gauguin</link> and try to reproduce
            the dynamic, user configurable, multi column display of the original Van Gogh website
            using the webcomponents provided by TEI Publisher. The corresponding webcomponents
            (<tag>pb-grid</tag>/<tag>pb-panel</tag>) have been reworked to make this possible.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Other New Features and Bug Fixes</title>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Sort and filter documents by title, author or file name</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Autocomplete suggestions are now displayed for all search boxes</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Allow arbitrary footnote labels to be passed via the @n parameter of the note behaviour</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Support plain images to be displayed by <tag>pb-facsimile</tag> - if a IIIF server is not needed or available</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Fix uploads of files containing spaces in their names</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Get It!</title>
        <para>TEI Publisher 4.1.0 is available as an application package on top of the <link xlink:href="https://exist-db.org">eXist XML Database</link>. Install it into a
            recent eXist (4.x.x series) by going to the dashboard and selecting TEI Publisher from
            the package manager.</para>
        <para>For more information refer to the <link xlink:href="https://teipublisher.com/exist/apps/tei-publisher/doc/documentation.xml">documentation</link> or visit the <link xlink:href="https://teipublisher.com">homepage</link> to play around with it.</para>
    </section>
</article>
